J Alan Brogan

Senior Software Engineer

Email: interviews@al-got-rhythm.net LinkedIn: https://ie.linkedin.com/in/algotrhythm

Summary

I enjoy an unrequited passion from decades of creating companies, teaching teams and releasing software. (With 10,000 hours as 1E) I have almost 5E engineering software on Unix networks and over 1E each in DevOps, Python, C++, Bash.

Interested in parsing, learning and knowledge.

My job is to make others's jobs easier, so I like the fewer procedures a smaller team needs, and the extra strands a diverse team finds. I like readability in code, ease in tools and chatting with friends

Experience

Senior Software Engineer at WWTS, September 2015 - present

Managing outsourced teams to move our Global Managed Services and others' onto the web. Tools: OSX, Linux, vim, Python, Flask, CSS, JavaScript, git, Slack, JIRA, GitLab, Nose, PEP8, Selenium, Chili, MySql, Postgresql

Senior SCM Engineer at S3 Group, January 2014 - August 2015 (1 year 6 months)

Secured significant contracts from blue chip clients for S3 Group, scripting the Blackduck suite of tools to ensure Open Source Licence (and other) compliance in source code from large teams of developers in multiple companies. Pleased to find that the pedantry honed on programming questions is just as useful to legal ones. Tools: OSX, Linux, Python, Bash, Git, Gerrit, Jenkins, Jira, ...

Interesting project: writing #licenses, #tags, ..., onto some Slack channels while conversing on others.

SCM at Altobridge, 2005 - December 2013 (8 years)

Helped to grow the team to 150+. I continuously integrated world-wide development teams and supported installation on a variety of platforms. We controlled release through Issue Trackers to System Test, Support and Customers, who provided mobile towers to remote lumberjacks (so we were OK). Led the team effort which achieved DO-178B certification of development processes, and contributed to the overall ISO-9000 certification efforts. I particularly enjoyed mentoring younger engineers, from internships through graduation and on to their own leadership positions. Tools: OSX, Linux, Python, Javascript, SVN, SQL, source code translation, Blackduck, Selenium.

Interesting Project: Was asked to optimise a Java program, so profiled it, then adapted a Python parser to take away the syntactic sugar leaving code frames which gcc recognised as C, with some #includes. Profiled it again, re-wrote the framework, profiled again, added features.

Co Founder at Omnify Systems Ltd, 2003 - 2005 (2 years)

Built a team to adapt retail software for use in the Irish Fashion industry. Tools: Delphi (Pascal), Microsoft SQL Server, TestComplete.

Interesting Project: Specification of a "tablet" for use by warehouse staff.

Leader at interWAVE, 1999 - 2003 (4 years)

On joining interWAVE I was responsible for transfer of the development of their OMC (Operations and Maintenance Centre) from Silicon Valley to Tralee, and then for all aspects of development in Tralee and for integration with other teams in America and China. Tools: C++, Solaris, Networking, Telecoms, Rational

Interesting question: why does your diff engine compare text, not code?

Co Founder at Microcellular, 1999 - 2001 (2 years)

I initially joined a startup company called Microcellular Systems, where we created a software team which developed software such as GSM subscriber management. This development team was a significant part of the reason why Microcellular was acquired by interWAVE. Enterprise Ireland helped us to attract talent from Tralee Institute of Technology which I built into a Team of 10 strong enough to be aquired by

Interesting Project: Mapping locations of approaching GSM towers from a shed. Tools: C, C++, Tcl/Tk, GSM, Windows

Coder at FlexTime, 1994 - 2000 (6 years)

I integrated the Flextime Windows-based system into the CSO (Central Statistics Office) VAX computers. Learned that the customer is always right, except when they think something might be "easy".

Interesting Project: Unit testing for The Millennium Bug. Tools: COBOL, VMS.

Ability Developer at National Training and Development Institute, 1995 - 1999 (4 years)

I helped differently abled people to use computers to better meet their needs. This was the toughest and most rewarding position I have undertaken.

Interesting challenge: Explain Visual Basic to a blind person who has heard Excel Macros. Listening to a program being read by a screen reader changes one's perspective, or one cannot help.

Teacher at Allied Computer Training, 1989 - 1994 (5 years)

Developed a 2-year City & Guilds certified Software Engineering course on an i386 running Microfsoft Unix, way back, when they were still nerds.

Volunteer Experience

Trainer at Centre for Talented Youth of Ireland, September 2011 - May 2012 (9 months)

Teaching kids to develop Andriod apps

Skills & Expertise

Unix, Linux, OS X, Xenix, Windows

Python, Bash, C, C++, SQL, JavaScript, HTML, COBOL, BASIC, Pascal, Tcl/Tk, Java

Git, Subversion, MySQL, Microsoft SQL Server, DO-178B, ISO 9001, GSM,

Team Building, Software Engineering, Software Development, Software Configuration Management, Continuous Integration, Testing, Test Automation, Database Administration, Server Administration, Change Management, Mobile Networks, Process Automation, Technical Training, Problem Solving

Software Licensing, Open Source Software, Parsing, Neural Networks

Projects

Open Source contributions

My Github projects and contributions are at https://github.com/jalanb

The community seems to like Copycat best, https://github.com/jalanb/co.py.cat But my favourite is Pym: https://github.com/jalanb/pym

My latest CV is at https://github.com/jalanb/al_got_rhythm.net/blob/master/cv/JAlanBrogan.pdf

Languages

English (Full professional proficiency)

German (Limited working proficiency)

Irish (Elementary proficiency)

Publications

Borland C++ Builder 6 Developers Guide

Sams December 30, 2002

Authors: J Alan Brogan, Jarrod Hollingworth, Bob Swart, Mark Cashman, Paul Gustavson

This book was created to fill the gaps in several areas of programming with C++Builder, and to provide content on many of the new features in C++Builder 5. It is aimed mostly at intermediate and advanced programmers, though several beginner chapters are included and many chapters contain lead-in information to get you up to speed. In total there are over 1750 pages of raw content!

A Python version of the Hofstadter Copycat algorithm

Authors: J Alan Brogan

Translation to Python of a Java implementation, with help from the Lisp in "Analogy Making as Perception" by Melanie Mitchell (a colleague of Douglas Hofstadter).

Education

Institute of Technology, Tralee

BSc, Computer Science, 2003 - 2004

Grade: Honours, First Class

Dublin City University

BSc, Computer Science, 1989 - 1992

Grade: Honours in all exams (but moved to Kerry before completion)

University College Dublin

Bachelor of Medicine, Bachelor of Surgery (M.B.B.S.), Medicine, 1979 - 1984

Grade: Honours in all exams, but left for the benefit of patients.

J Alan Brogan

https://ie.linkedin.com/in/algotrhythm

Colleagues have recommended Alan

- "I was very lucky to have Alan as my manager. His enthusiasm for coding was infectious and he is a remarkable programmer."
- Geraldine Patton, Software Engineer, Altobridge, reported to Alan at Altobridge
- "A fantastic boss; inspires great enthusiasm and sets a high standard. Alan really loves what he does, and is a great mentor and organiser for colleagues..."
- Laurence Dusoswa, Software Engineer, Altobridge, reported to Alan at Altobridge
- "Alan was very motivating in his role and encouraging to anyone that worked with him. He was always helpful and a great mentor. He was very enthusiastic in his role and a pleasure to work with and for."
- Maeve Nolan, Software Manager, Alvarion, reported to Alan at interWAVE

A random redditor has recommended Alans code

Impressive, not only for the thinking of the idea but there is something I love about how simple it is and it is bash

I love witty code snippets

— /u/andru183, *Redditor*, commented on my code at /r/commandline/